[
    {
        "question": "He is (<em>strang</em>) #### ðonne ic⁠ — He is stronger than I",
        "correctAnswer": "strengra",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'strang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'streng', and takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'strengra' because it is related to the masculine nominative 'he'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "strengran",
                "explanation": "This adjective is modifying the subject 'he' so it declines using the weak nominative masculine 'a' ending to become 'strengra'"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "strangra",
                "explanation": "The stem of 'strang' undergoes 'i-mutation' so the 'a' becomes 'e', meaning 'strang' becomes 'strengra' in the comparative"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Bebead he ðæt him mon (<em>lang</em>) #### cwidas beforan cwæde, and he symle gedefelice æftercwæþ⁠ — He ordered longer sayings to be spoken before him, and he always repeated them properly",
        "correctAnswer": "lengran",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and it takes the weak accusative plural suffix 'ran' to become 'lengran' as it is modifying the noun 'cwid'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "langran",
                "explanation": "The stem of 'lang' undergoes 'i-mutation' so the 'a' becomes 'e', meaning 'lang' becomes 'lengran' in the comparative"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "lengra",
                "explanation":"Here 'lang' takes the weak accusative plural suffix 'ran' to become 'lengran' as it is modifying the noun 'cwid'"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "langra",
                "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and it takes the weak accusative plural suffix 'ran' to become 'lengran' as it is modifying the noun 'cwid'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic in wite sceal bidan in bendum ond me (<em>god</em>) #### ham for oferhygdum æfre ne wene⁠ — I must in torment abide in bonds, and never hope for any better home for my pride",
        "correctAnswer": "beteran",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'god' is irregular and modifying the masculine noun 'ham' so it takes the ending 'an' to become 'beteran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se horshwæl biþ micle (<em>lytel</em>) #### ðonne oðre hwalas⁠ — The walrus is much smaller than other whales",
        "correctAnswer": "læssa",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'lytel' is irregular and related to the subject 'horshwæl' so it becomes 'læssa'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic towurpe mine bernu and ic wyrce (<em>micel</em>) #### bernu⁠ — I will tear down my barns and I will build bigger barns",
        "correctAnswer": "maran",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'micel' is irregular and modifying the neuter accusative noun 'bernu⁠' so it takes the 'an' suffix to become 'maran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt læstede þa xix wintra þa hwile þe Stephne cyning wæs one æfre hit wæs (<em>yfel</em>) #### ond wiersa⁠ — That lasted 19 winters while Stephen was king and ever it was worse and worse",
        "correctAnswer": "wiersa",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'yfel' is irregular and related to the subject 'hit' so it becomes 'wiersa' in the comparative",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Næfre he ær ne siððan (<em>heard</em>) #### hæle fand⁠ — Never before or since did he find a stouter warrior",
        "correctAnswer": "heardran",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' is modifying the accusative masculine noun 'hæle' so it takes the 'ran' suffix to become 'heardran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wisa, hwilc cræft þe geþuht betwux þas (<em>furðre</em>) #### wesan⁠ — Teacher, which craft do you think is the greater?",
        "correctAnswer": "furþra|furðra",
        "explanation":"Here 'furðre' is related to the masculine subject 'cræft' so it loses its 're' and takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'furðra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se wudu is eastlang and westlang hund twelftiges mila lang oððe (<em>lang</em>) ####⁠ — The wood, from east to west, is twelve hundred miles long or longer",
        "correctAnswer": "lengra",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and is related to the masculine subject 'wudu' so it takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'lengra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæm (<em>mild</em>) #### cyninge Wihtræde rixigendum⁠ — In the reign of the kindest king Wihtræd",
        "correctAnswer": "mildostan",
        "explanation":"Here 'mild' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the weak genitive suffix 'an', as it comes after the definitive article 'þam'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se lichoma ðonne on ðone (<em>heard</em>) #### stenc and on ðone fulostan biþ gecyrred⁠ — The body then shall be turned to the strongest and foulest stench",
        "correctAnswer": "heardostan",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the weak accusative suffix 'an', as it comes after the definitive article 'ðone'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Cwædon ðæt he wære manna (<em>mild</em>) #### and monþwærost⁠ — They said that he was kindest and most courteous of men",
        "correctAnswer": "mildost",
        "explanation":"Here 'mild' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and no other suffix as it is strong related to the masculine subject 'he'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He sohte fram ðæm ieldestan oþ ðone (<em>geong</em>) ####⁠ — He searched from the eldest to the youngest",
        "correctAnswer": "gingestan",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'geong' undergoes i-mutation to become 'ging', and takes the superlative suffix 'est' and the weak accusative suffix 'an', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'ðone'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic gyrne fultum ðinre foreþingrædene ðu (<em>halig</em>) #### mægden and þrowystr⁠ — I earnestly impolore your help, you holiest maiden and martyr",
        "correctAnswer": "haligoste",
        "explanation":"Here 'halig' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the strong accusative feminine suffix 'e' as it is modifying 'mægden'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "haligost",
                "explanation": ""
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se wæs on lare and on dæde se (<em>heah</em>) ####⁠ — He was in learning and in deed the highest",
        "correctAnswer": "hiehsta",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'heah' undergoes i-mutation to become 'hieh', and takes the superlative suffix 'st' and the weak nominative masculine suffix 'a', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'se'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "hiehost|hiehest",
                "explanation":"Because 'heah' ends in a 'h', it drops the vowel in 'ost' to take the superlative suffix 'st'. Since it modifies a weak nominative masculine noun, it also takes the suffix 'a'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "He me sealde ðæt (<em>god</em>) #### hors⁠ — He gave me the best horse",
        "correctAnswer": "betest",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'god' is irregular, becoming 'betest' in the superlative. It takes no suffix because 'hors' is neuter and neuter accusative forms take no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Sceal beon se (<em>lytel</em>) #### dæl nyhst þæm tune ðe se deada man on lið⁠ — The smallest portion shall be closest to where the dead man lies",
        "correctAnswer": "læsta",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'lytel' is irregular, becoming 'læst' in the superlative. It takes the weak nominative masculine ending 'a' to become 'læsta', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'se'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hit is ealra wyrta (<em>micel</em>) ####⁠ — It is greatest of all herbs",
        "correctAnswer": "mæst",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'micel' is irregular, becoming 'mæst' in the superlative. It takes no suffix because it relates to the neuter 'hit' and neuter accusative forms take no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se deofol sloh lob mid ðære (<em>yfel</em>) #### wunde⁠ — The devil slew Job with the worst of wounds",
        "correctAnswer": "wierstan",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'yfel' is irregular, becoming 'wierst' in the superlative. It takes the weak genitive feminine ending 'an' to become 'wierstan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
        
    },
    {
        "question": "Se biscop is lareowa (<em>halig</em>) ####⁠ — The bishop is the holiest of teachers",
        "correctAnswer": "haligost",
        "explanation":"Here 'halig' takes the -ost ending of superlative adjectives",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "þis stan is hwit, þis stan is hwitra, ac þas stanas sind (<em>hwit</em>) ####⁠ — This stone is white, this stone is whiter, but these stones are whitest",
        "correctAnswer": "hwitost",
        "explanation":"Here 'hwit' takes the -ost ending of superlative adjectives",
        "commonMistakes": []
        
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo is (<em>leoht</em>) ####⁠ þonne mona — She is brighter than the moon",
        "correctAnswer": "leohtre",
        "explanation":"Here 'leoht' takes the -re ending because it is related to the feminine 'heo' so it declines in line with the feminine weak to become 'leohtre'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hit is (<em>swift</em>) ####⁠ þonne sunne — I am swifter than the sun",
        "correctAnswer": "swiftre",
        "explanation":"Here 'swift' takes the -re ending because it is related to the neuter 'hit' so it declines in line with the neuter weak to become 'swiftre'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Emne swa þa woruldgeþingu beoþ (<em>micel</em>) — Just as the secular powers are greater",
        "correctAnswer": "maran",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'micel' is irregular and modifying the plural noun 'woruldgeþingu' so it takes the 'an' suffix to become 'maran'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]